this is a ninja supplier Sundin Sutan
mmm suitable for the imperturbable much
Monica 106 thus have I heard in one
occasion the Buddha was living among the
Kurus in the town of the Kurus called
camasta Tama there the blessed one
addressed the bhikkhus because yes
Bunton those because replied the Blessed
One said this because sense desires are
impermanent empty false deceptive that
which is fraudulent because is the
utterance of a fool because whatever
sends desires here and now and whatever
sends desires in lives to come whatever
perceptions of sense desires here and
now and whatever perceptions of sense
desires in lives to come both of these
are martyrs realm modest province modest
bait modest feeding ground so the thing
to note here is that whatever sends
desires here and now and whatever sends
his eyes in lives to come means whatever
senses are as a present and whatever
possibilities of sense desires are also
present right here right now as
possibilities that's the important thing
to discern because seeing for example in
that isn't sensual desire right here
right now and overcoming it on that
basis through thinking there about non
attractive or how dangerous it is and so
on that's all fine but what one person
also needs to see is the simultaneously
present possibilities of sensuality for
the future so you might deal with a
particular arising of sensual desire but
you also want to deal with what's
peripheral to that particular arising
which is possibilities for more arising
not now later so even if you overcome
a particular sensual desire that has
arisen you want to you don't want to
rest so to speak in that overcoming but
you want to see that the possibilities
of these things being manifested again
tomorrow in next day and in two years in
10 years in ten lifetimes
you want to see that that's still
present and above all it's still
applicable to you so that's why the one
who reflects rightly needs to include it
in the reflection that not just the
present sensuality it's it's impermanent
empty false deceptive it should be
unwanted but also that liability to
future sensuality as well should be seen
the same that's how you truly surmount
the entire domain not just a particular
manifestation of it this forum here
these evil unwholesome things lead to
mental covetousness ill-will and anger
they create an obstacle for a noble
disciple in training here so they create
an obstacle for somebody who has the
right view at least and yes that's it
said in other cities as well
a noble disciple sawed open or higher
will could be no it's not a guarantee
but it could be distracted still with
sensuality with sense desires by not
fully dwelling on the danger of it so it
says in this case a bhikkhu a noble
disciple of like to us whatever sins
desire here and now whatever sense
desires in lives to come whatever
perceptions of sense desires here and
now whatever perceptions of sense
desires in lives to come and again this
is if anybody wonders whether it it
means as a possibility future it does
because how could you be perceiving
sense desires in lives to come when
those lives are in there and that's the
whole point you don't want to wait for
the every manifestation of sensuality to
arise and affect you you want to see it
on the level of possibility and that is
the peripheral level in regard to the
actually Karan
particularly present sensuality and
central domain so whatever perceptions
of these possibilities you have as in
whatever perceptions and sells desires
and lives to come you want to see that
as well as pertaining to the perceptions
of sensuality here and now says both of
these things might as well modest
Provins modest bait modest feeling
around here these evil unwholesome
things lead to mental covetousness
ill-will and anger they create an
obstacle for a noble disciple in
training here what if I were to dwell
with a mind that is large expanded
having mentally determined to surmount
the world and again this is not we spoke
about this before in the in the few
talks on meditation how to establish in
mind but that's exactly what it says
expanded mind so to speak means mind
that has overcome through including the
discernment of both particular
sensuality and the domain of the
peripherally possible sensual experience
so without a particular manifestation
and that's how you go truly beyond the
entire domain of sensuality as I just
said so the mind then gets expanded
beyond it so it's been large having
mentally determined to surmount the
world which is what sensuality is for
somebody who stood bound with sensual
desire so surmounting expanding
establishing in my own bhavet and
lodging it whatever word you use that's
the point
not just overcoming one particular
perception of sensuality that's
currently a reason and enduring for you
but you want to start discerning
possibilities of being affected by
sensuality in the future that also but
takes in the domain of particularly
present enduring sensuality for you so
in the same manner then when there is no
particular manifestation of some sensual
desire you could you could review your
mind and see okay so maybe there is no
particular manifestation of sensuality
is bothering me now but it would that be
true for the future will in the future
when there when the central object
manifest themselves will I also remain
unbothered by it if the answer is no
means the mind hasn't been loud and
large expanded and mentally determined
to surmount the world so for somebody
with the right view they realize they
only need to do is maintain the
establishment of the mind on that
expanded level expanded is a relative
sense of course but expanded in a sense
of surmounting and having included both
particular sensuality and possibilities
of sensualities in the lives to come
included and and just don't descend down
on their level because dwelling with the
mind that is large expanded having
mentally determinism on the world there
will be none of this evil and also
mental covetousness ill-will and anger
because mental culture sense evil and
anger need the central domain as its
basis having surmounted the entire
century domain correctly which means
you're not contacted by it then ill-will
covetousness and anger cannot affect you
i that they cannot manifest having
abandoned these the the novel sap
reflects whether my mind will be
unlimited unbounded and well-developed
that's exactly that's exactly we just
described large expanded and so on means
unlimited by centrality unbounded I
could uncontrolled not liable to it
well-developed having practiced this way having often
having practiced this way having often
dwell levies his mind helps clarity in
this domain and that's another thing so
the mind gets established upon this
right type of thoughts thoughts of the
central domain correctly not miss
conceiving it not ignoring and not not
seeing it
thoughts of liability to future
sensuality so when the mind is properly
established then the monkey Wells in
that state as in it's not a meditative
experience where he is frozen into means
the mind has reflected correctly
samantha things that need to be
surmounted keeps a watchful eye on greed
aversion delusion to not manifest
because they would mean he has gone back
into that domain where these things
manifest so he goes around
he's day dwelling in this
that's that's exactly means having often
dwelled like this so he spends time in
it
his minds develop clarity in this domain
with clarity either he enters upon the
imperturbable now or he inclines the
world with understanding again clarity
of what and Peter Bible is understanding
of what the table imperturbable is
that's that's that's how he enters it
that's how he develops it imperturbable
means impotent by sensuality means the
possibility of sensual domain cannot
distract one anymore because he dwell
long enough away from it and it says on
the breakup of the body after death
it is possible that consciousness that
has been involved with this will reach
the imperturbable that means that
consciousness that has been involved
with this means he's been making these
phenomena and you're presently for him
as in somebody can just think about
imperturbable that's one thing but
another thing is to to think rightly
about the immaterial domain develop
understanding and then dwell in it by
dwelling in it that domain is present
for you whenever there is presence
that's what consciousness is so through
often dwelling in such a phenomenon if
the imperturbable domain there has
surmounted sensuality his consciousness
has been involved with this sufficiently
and because of that in the moment after
death if could it could reach the
imperturbable so that's the first way
suitable for the imperturbable the
second way is noble disciple who
reflects thus whatever sense desire is
here and now whatever sense desires in
lives to come whatever perceptions of
sense desires here and now whatever
perceptions of sense desires in life's
to come whatever matter all matter is
the four Great elements and from the
four Great elements matter is assumed
method it held up methods misconceived
see just there
so when he plates in this way having
often draw like this his mind develops
clarity in this domain with clarity
enters upon the imperturbable or he
inclines towards with understanding on
the breakup of the body after death it
is possible that the consciousness
involved with this or will reach the
imperturbable this is a second way so
here one might wonder why this will talk
about sensuality sensual designs in
life's to come and then all metal is of
all great elements in from for grandmas
matter is a stew where's the connection
there well the connection there is can
you even think about any central object
of any sense if there is no an actual
factual material presence existence of
that thing
if there is no matter to be assumed
how can there be attraction to a
material form of any kind
how can they be lost to words it so in
the heart of any and every sensuality
here and now in the heart of every
possibility of sensuality for the lives
to come one thing that's universally in
common is that independence of four
Great elements independence of material
aspect which means anything sensual an
essential object is completely
circumstantial accidental you could even
say not that your sensuality in your
sensual preferences and prolific
proliferation is is accidental but the
material aspect of every central object
could have not been literally it is but
it could have not been and that's the
whole point for great elements as in
this so great
you can't even appropriate and let alone
have them in and and regard them is
yours and have them obey your will and
so on so and that's that's in like even
if you possess the central object in its
heart the material the materiality of
the central object is something utterly
inaccessible to you and you can apply
the same to your own body to the body of
others to the
sense objects to your own senses it's
it's utterly enclosed so the entire
central domain is utterly enclosed
within the material domain and as such
it's it's it's inaccessible it's just
you cannot even conceive how to come
underneath so to speak and truly own it
so you can only entertain the notion of
ownership through get seriously taking
for granted the the offered careless
pleasure in regard to it the pleasure
the the distraction then you get through
through the SATA satisfying that that
possibility of pleasure on that surface
but that cannot uphold then pick up that
whole sensual domain and make it yours
despite what the sensuality tells you
that's why the when I say it's a fraud
it deceives it's a bait you jump on it
thinking I'll have this failing to see
that it contains a hook that actually
hooks you up and baits you like a fish
dances furthermore because a noble
disciple of like thus whatever senses I
was here and now whatever sense desires
in life's to come with our perceptions
of senses as he turn on with our
perceptions of sensitizing lives to come
whatever met her here and now whatever
met her in lives to come whatever
perception of meta here now would have
perceptional method in lives to come
both of these are impermanent whatever
is impermanent
it's not worth delighting it in other
word welcoming nor becoming attached to
so this is just the same extension
extension of the same thing we just
discussed in the previous woman you are
assuming that the four Great elements
you take that whole fundamental domain
the determines the sensuality in which
sense meta here access Sankara but if
somebody fails to see it on that level
you take that aspect matter being the
center of your sensuality being a
determination being the inseparable from
sensuality is inseparable from material
as we just said so what is the main
characteristic of
of determinations in general what is the
universal property of them the
properties it cannot be own determinations have
it cannot be own determinations have
arisen on their own that's what on each
is the properties it's impermanent it's
subject when you can't even conceive it
like how could you decide what it's
subjected to your invisible to it you
detect the determinations the structure
determinations the presence of matter
and so on it they don't see you you
don't exist for it
so whatever perceptions of matter here
are now with our perceptions of matter
in lives to come to the same principle
as it is with the with the sensuality
not just the presently arisen since
reality that's inseparable from the
matter but also the possibility of
matter through the possibility of future
sensualities so whatever perceptions are
matter here and now without perceptions
are met in lives to come both of these
are impermanent so as we said it's that
impossibility to own of the matter that
is inseparable from sensuality whatever
cannot be owned
whatever has a reason on its own
whatever it's virtually accidental and
and and circumstantial that is not worth
delighting in its own word appropriate
he needed some world welcoming it it's
not worth becoming attached to when he
practices in this way having often
dualities his mind develops clarity in
his domain with a clarity he enters upon
the imperturbable now or he inclines the
world with understanding on the breakup
of the body after death it is possible
that the consciousness involved with
this will reach the imperturbable this
because is declared to be the third way
which is suitable for the imperturbable
furthermore because a nobody disciple
reflects does whatever sends desires
here and now whatever sent desires in
lives to come but our perceptions of
sense desires here and now what our
perceptions of sense desires and lives
to come
whatever matter here and now whatever
matter in lives to come whatever
perceptions of matter here and now and
whatever perceptions of met
in life's to come and whatever
perceptions of imperturbability all our
perceptions
where did wherever these seas with other
reminder this is peaceful this is a
blind the domain of nothingness for one
who practices in this way he is one who
often dwells like this his mind develops
clarity in this domain and so on with a
clarity and his upon domain of
nothingness and he inclines towards
understanding breakup after death it's
possible that consciousness involved
with this will reach the domain of
nothingness so the the perceptions of
sense desires the perceptions of
possibilities of sense desire the
perceptions of the matter that
determines the perceptions of the sense
desires the perception of the method a
determines the possibilities of sense
desires the perception of imperturbable
as in the perception of the surmounted
domain of all of this all these are
perceptions wherever these perception
sees without reminder which is in
nothingness the absence of perceptions
this is peaceful this is sublime that
domain and says furthermore because a
noble disciple gone to the forest even
gone to the root of a tree or gone to an
antique dwelling reflects thus this is
empty of self all of what belongs to
self for one who practices in this way
he's the one who often dwells like this
his mind develops clarity in this domain
so because the noble disciples gone to
the forest gone to the root of a tree
continent is running so a monk having
gone and become physically secluded from
everyone and everything he reflects thus
and that's why it's necessary he can't
be with other people and say this is
empty of self because the mind will say
well okay you are empty yourself but
external counterpart of you is not empty
of self or he might not be empty of self
so the basis for this reflection needs
to be physical solitude and it says this
is empty of self or what belongs to self
so again it's empty of the actually a
reason present
sends herself or it's empty oh and it's
also empty of anything that belongs to
and might belong to self in other words
the self is not present it's not implied
neither through the presently arisen
things that self can own nor is it imply
through the possibility of future
arising of things that self can own and
the one who practices in this way he's
the one who dwells like this and it will
develop quiet in this domain and that's
why this is listed after these three
ways of imperturbable and the nothing is
because it's the same practice just in
regard to the different reflecting on
different things so with clarity he
enters upon the domain of nothingness he
inclines towards it with an
understanding on the breakup of the body
after death it is possible that the
conscience involved with this will reach
the domain of nothingness this is the
second way suitable for the domain of
nothingness furthermore a bhikkhu
bhikkhus a noble disciple reflects thus
I am NOT in anything anywhere for anyone
and there isn't anything mind anywhere
for anyone but one who practices in this
way he's often he's the one who often
grows lettuce and so on so this this is
now the extension Nissen of the same
reflection just taking like like more a
more personal approach or rather person
approach from from more personal side as
opposed to sensuality the
inaccessibility of matter the two are
inseparable from each other so you end
up overcoming the sensuality to that but
if you if you approach it differently or
if you take it further you would see
that even once you have surmounted the
central domain you could see that what's
there what's there left your experience
as a whole it's not in anything anywhere
for anyone as in notice that you cannot
own it but anyone who ever has a notion
of self cannot own it either anywhere in
the world so and there isn't anything
mine anywhere for anyone nor is there
anything anyone's for me for that matter
so this is the third way suitable for
the nothingness further noble disciple
reflects das whatever sense desires here
and now whatever
thousand lives to come whatever
perceptions of sense desires here and
now what our perceptions of sense
desires in life to come whatever matter
here and now whatever matter in life to
come whatever perceptions of matter here
now but a perception of mental life to
come what our perceptions have repented
in palpability and whatever perceptions
of the domain of nothingness
all of that is perception and we
mentioned that in order to talk the
absence of of something is perceived as
nothing so nothingness is perceived
whatever this ceases with other reminder
this is peaceful that's sublime which is
a domain of neither perception or no
perception so the same principle of
development of the mind the same
principle of establishment Samadhi and
clarity just taking a note further so
the one who practices in this way the
often well that is with clarity hands
upon the domain of neither perception
nor perception he inclines towards it
with understanding on the break up of
the body of the death it is possible the
consciousness involved this with reach
of the made of neither perception of
perception after the Buddha finished
this description of these establishments
the venerable anchor said to this said
this to the Blessed One he burnt the
vicar practices in this way it might not
be and it might not be mine it will not
be and it will not be mine whatever
there is whatever exists that I am
abandoning in this way he obtains
indifference Bunty could he be fully
extinguished or might not be fully
extinguished and under in this case some
because might be fully extinguished and
some might not be fully extinguished
what is the reason what is the cause why
by some because my not be fully
extinguish and we're not and some will
be fully he ran under Baku prize in this
way it might not be and it might not be
mine it will not be and it will not be
mine whatever there is whatever exists
that I am abandoning in this way he
obtains indifference he delights in this
indifference welcomes it remains
attached to it for one delighting in
this indifference welcoming in the
military there is consciousness
dependent on it assumed by it another
bit assumption is not fully extinguished
but when there is
but where does that assuming because
soon his assumption ananda is on the
level of the domain of neither
perception or perception so surely this
assuming because seems the best
assumption then indeed ananda this
assuming be consumes the best assumption
this Ananda is the best assumption that
is the domain of neither perception nor
non-perception so if you remember in the
beginning of this talk when we said the
the presence of matter is accidental and
you realize that you realize that this
method it's here that I'm currently
attracted to say some sense object this
matter that it's here it could have not
been and that's that's that's what I
mean when we say it's inaccessible to
you you can't even conceive where it
came from you're invisible to it it's
there but it could have not been and
something that could have not been you
recognize it will not be so all that is
on the level of the present there is a
thing and now you do the same for the
possibilities to it
they're also present on the peripheral
level so then it's not just oh this
present there is a matter that is
accidental it could have not arisen it
will not arise but then you take it
further that which has arisen because of
that accident ality so to speak cannot
be mine which means any future things
that might arise they will arise that
could arise well they will for sure not
arise for me so setting your mind up
upon such reflection establishing an in
it means whatever arises sensual or non
central it's seen as accidental is seen
as impermanent is seen as it cannot be
on it seen as an each other so then
having a reflection it might not be and
it might not be for me it will not be it
will not be mine because if there is if
there is a sense of it might in regard
to your own sense of control and
ownership means it won't means you are
not the owner if there is a possibility
of things to not be yours means you are
not really in charge of deciding which
things are yours and that's how you
realize that it might not be it might
not be mine
it will not be it will not be mine it
cannot be it cannot be mine you could
say like that
and then it says whatever there is
whatever exists whatever can manifest
whatever I could own through my own
ignorance well I'm abandoning like this because I
well I'm abandoning like this because I
see it as impossible to own and that's
why he obtains a Pecha as a result of it
a complete indifference but he doesn't
see that indifference is also something
that has arisen a phenomenon that could
have not been pretty much if he doesn't
abandon that - well he will remain a
bound with his assumption of this is
mine but as the Buddha said that
assumption has basically abandoned the
whole world now abandoned the perception
and it's established upon the per se
abandoned the perception abandoned the
nothingness and it's established upon
the basis of neither perception or
perception that's what it corresponds to
that way of thinking corresponds to the
basis of neither perception nor
non-perception and it says this Ananda
is the best type of assumption it's the
best type of Rupa Donna so if anybody
would hold on to domain of neither
perception or perception they would
abandon pretty much everything virtually
everything so very little left to do and
says here on on the bigger practices in
this way it might not be and it might
not be mine
thus it will not be it will not be mine
whatever there is whatever exists that I
am abandoning in this way he obtains
indifference he does not delight in it
he does not welcome it he does not
remain attached to it for not delighting
in for the one not delighting and
indifference not welcoming or remaining
attached to it consciousness is not
dependent on it not assumed by it and
there are no assumptions and bhiku
without any assumption is the one who is
fully extinguished and then the mmm they
were no one in the summarizes wonderful
bunty marvelous truly he has been
declared by the Blessed One the means by
which there is the crossing of the flood
but one bhante which is a noble
liberation here on under a noble
disciple reflects thus whatever since
desires here and now whatever
possibilities of sense desires in
to come whatever perceptions of senses
whatever possibilities of sense desires
now ending lives to come whatever
perceptions of senses are here and now
what our perceptions are send desires as
a possibilities now and in lives to come
whatever matter here an hour whatever
matter in the future
whatever perception the matter here and
now would have perceptions of matter in
lives to come whatever perceptions of
imperative ability and whatever
perceptions of the domain of nothingness
and whatever perceptions of the domain
of neither perception nor perception
this is the personality this is the
extent of personality means this is the
extent as far as the assumption can go
as far as you padana can reach you
surmount the extent you have surmounted
the basis of appropriation the basis of
open on on the basis of personality just
as I said up there by surmounting the
central domain you've surmounted the
domain upon which greed you will
delusion manifest as a basis so you
don't stop your greed aversion illusion
voluntarily you remove its necessary
basis so in the same sense you can't say
oh I'm not a person I'll decide to be or
not a person and I'll decide to
extinguish the slightest traces of my
personality you can do that but what you
can do is surmount the basis of
personality not delighting in it not as
humid see it is accidentally arisen
impermanent impossible to own and there
will be the cessation of personality and
it says but this is the deathless this
is the liberation of the mind without
assumptions the sananda the way suitable
for imperturbable has been taught by me
the way suitable for the domain of
nothingness has been taught the way
suitable for the domain of neither
perception nor perception has been
taught by the means of which there is
the crossing of the flood no liberation
has been taught under whatever should be
done by the teacher for the welfare of
the disciples compassionate out of
compassion this has been done by me for
you these and under our roots of trees
these are empty dwellings meditator
under the node bin elegent do not be the
one who regrets later this is our
instruction to you
so that was Najma